Finding Aid for School of Information (University of Michigan) Records 1901-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Office files 1904-2001
  - 1969-2001
    - Coordinating Committee for Strategic Planning 1986 (Box 39)
    - Core Curriculum Task Force 1992-1995 (Box 39)
    - Course Descriptions, scattered and various dates (Box 39)
    - Courses on School and Children 1947-1956 (Box 39)
    - Course Syllabi for Adjunct Professors 1988-1993 (Box 39)
    - Curriculum Committee
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1969-1970 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1970-1971 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1980-1981 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1981-1982 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1982-1983 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1983-1984 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1985-1989 (Box 39)
      - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1989-1990 (Box 39)
    - Curriculum Discussion Group 1959-1960 (Box 39)
    - Curriculum (proposed) 1985-1986 (Box 39)
    - Curriculum Task Force 1985-1986 (Box 39)
    - Dean's Report to the Alumni 1978 (Box 39)
    - Degrees Awarded 1978 (Box 40)
    - Digital/Photo/CD project on the History of the Health Sciences with Steneck/Anne (1993-1995) (Box 40)
    - Executive Committee Material 1979-1993 (Box 40)
    - Faculty Appointments and Sabbaticals 1982-1985 (Box 40)
    - Faculty Brainstorming Sessions 1993 (Box 40)
    - Faculty Profiles and Curriculum Vita (Box 40)
    - Faculty Memorandums, (mainly e-mail) 1992-1993 (Box 40)
    - Fifty year report, "...the more it is the same: Fifty years of Library Science Graduates at the U-M," 1978 (Box 40)
    - Master course list 1966-1979 (Box 40)
    - Master course list 1980-1990 (Box 40)
    - Neal, Homer, correspondence 1996-1997 (Box 40)
    - News Releases
      - 1979 (Box 40)
      - 1980 (Box 40)
      - 1981 (Box 40)
      - 1982 (Box 40)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 40)
      - 1989-1994 (Box 40)
    - Oversized recruiting posters (8), not dated (Box 40)
    - Policy, Criteria for Promotion and Tenure 1979 (Box 40)
    - Proposals 1993-1995 (Box 40)
    - Recruiting Materials, various dates (Box 40)
    - Research Seminar (Engineering) 1989-1990 (Box 40)
    - Research Task Force 1983-1987 (Box 40)
    - Research, University of Michigan-World (Box 40)
    - Request for Approval of Course Change 1985-1986 (Box 40)
    - School Name and Mission Statements, various dates and undated (Box 40)
    - Strategic Planning Activities 1984-1988 (Box 40)
    - Student and Alumni Questionnaires (Box 40)
    - Time Schedules 1973-1988 (Box 40)
    - Warner, Robert M., correspondence 1988-1989 (Box 40)
    - Computer Disks 1983-1990, circa 1983-1990, 42 floppy disks 5.25" (Box 40)
      (mainly unlabeled)
  - 1954-1996
    The Office Files, 1954-1996,subseries (1.25 linear feet, 1954-1996) is mainly comprised of materials relating to the American Library Association accreditation process and review. Materials also include proposals for the Title II B Library and Education and Human Resource Development Program.
    - American Library Association Accreditation 1954-1982
      - Annual Report to American Library Association and related background materials
        - 1953-1954 (Box 43)
        - 1964 (Box 43)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 43)
        - 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 43)
        - 1969-1970 (Box 43)
        - 1970-1971 (Box 43)
        - 1979-1980 (Box 43)
        - 1980-1981 (Box 43)
    - Correspondence, general, American Library Association 1954-1972 (Box 43)
    - North Central Accreditation 1980 (Box 43)
    - Self-Study Report, Committee on Accreditation of the American Library Association
      - 1974 vol. I and II (Box 43)
      - 1982 vol. I and II (Box 43)
    - Higher Education Act Title II-B Grant (Grant and associated materials)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 43)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 43)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 43)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 43)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 43)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 43)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 43)
      - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 43)
      - 1996-1997, 3 folders (Box 44)
      - 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 44)
- Dean's Files
  The Dean's Files series is organized in subseries by dean. The records supplement the Office Files and also may include material on the dean's personal and professional life and activities.
  - Dean Russell E. Bidlack
    The Russell E. Bidlack subseries, which includes material received in several accessions, is divided into Personal and Administrative Files, Faculty Correspondence, Statistics, Topical Files and Miscellaneous Files
    The Personal and Administrative Files consist of correspondence, reports, lectures and speeches and professional papers. Although most of this material is personal, much of the correspondence does relate to the administration of the school. There are five major files: American Library Association (ALA); Association of American Library Schools (AALS); Consulting; Correspondence; and Lectures, Papers, Publications, Speeches, and Testimony.
    The ALA and AALS files consist of materials that document Bidlack's participation in various committees and projects. Listed ALA committees include: Accreditation, Professional Ethics, History Section, Nominating, Standards, and Statistics. For the AALS, the information is available on Deans and Directors, Statistics, and Tele-colloquia.
    Bidlack's service on the ALA Committee on Accreditation (COA) is the most extensive and best documented. There is material on Bidlack's co-writing of the COA Standards for Evaluation in 1972. There is also correspondence regarding surveys and questionnaires Bidlack sponsored on the accreditation process. The bulk of the material relates to his participation on COA visiting committees to various library schools.
    Consulting is a file relating to Bidlack's work as a consultant. Between 1970 and 1984, he visited and evaluated numerous library schools, assisting with accreditation and self-study. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    Correspondence is arranged both topically and chronologically. The topical portion consists primarily of correspondence with various individuals. Of particular interest here is Bidlack's frequent correspondence with Dean Edward Holley of the library school at the University of North Carolina. The letters provide insight into the problems of library school administration. The chronological files are more extensive, touching on a wide variety of subjects.
    Lectures, Papers, Publications, Speeches, and Testimony files contain materials relating to presentations by Bidlack. In some cases, there is correspondence in addition to the text of the presentation. This is especially the case with Bidlack's testimony before Congress and his 1979 paper, "The Place of Specialization in the Master's Degree."
    The Faculty Correspondence and Topical Files sub-subseries complement items found in the earlier accessions. Correspondence consists mostly of memos from Bidlack to the faculty and from the faculty to him. These provide a good source of information on the daily activities of the school and issues that were being dealt with by the faculty as a whole. The Statistics series contains statistics on every aspect of the school from number of students to break downs on faculty grade distributions. Many of these statistics were used for reports, both for university and non-university purposes.
    - Personal and Administrative Papers
      - American Library Association
        - Committee on Accreditation (Box 15)
          - Affirmative Action 1975 (Box 15)
          - Bidlack questionnaire 1976, 2 folders (Box 15)
          - Bidlack survey (on use of advisory committees) 1979 (Box 15)
          - Site visits
            - Denver Spring 1974 (Box 15)
            - Chicago October 1974 (Box 15)
            - San Jose State 1974-1976
              - Correspondence (Box 15)
              - Documents (Box 15)
            - Clarion October 1975 (Box 15)
            - Mankato April 1976 (Box 15)
            - Texas Women's 1981 (Box 15)
            - Missouri 1982 (Box 15)
          - Standards for Evaluation (Box 15)
          - Swanson, Asheim, and Bidlack Report (on nominating procedure to COA) 1978 (Box 15)
          - Totten and Cassata book (article by Bidlack on accreditation) 1973 (Box 15)
        - Committee on Professional Ethics 1979-1981 (Box 15)
        - Conferences 1978-1983 (Box 15)
        - Dewey Award Committee 1974 (Box 15)
        - Dewey Award Jury 1981-1982 (Box 15)
        - History Section 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - Nominating Committee, RASD 1972-1975 (Box 15)
        - Nominating Committee 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - Standards Committee 1968-1977 (Box 15)
        - Statistics Committee 1979-1980 (Box 15)
        - Wedgeworth letter (on petition candidates) 1980 (Box 15)
      - American Library History Round Table 1974 (Box 15)
      - Association of American Library Schools
        - Bidlack, Bunge, Farley Committee (on the need for annual statistics) 1977-1978 (Box 15)
        - Council of Deans and Directors 1978-1979 (Box 15)
        - Statistics Coordinating Committee 1979-1981 (Box 15)
        - Tele-colloquia Committee 1981 (Box 15)
      - Consulting
        - Alabama 1972 (Box 16)
        - Albany 1980 (Box 16)
        - Ball State 1972 (Box 16)
        - Case Western 1982 (Box 16)
        - Jackson Library 1981 (Box 16)
        - Kent State 1978 (Box 16)
        - Louisiana State 1982 (Box 16)
        - Maryland 1979 (Box 16)
        - Missouri 1984 (Box 16)
        - North Carolina (Chapel Hill) 1978 (Box 16)
        - North Carolina (Greensboro) 1978 (Box 16)
        - North Texas State 1970 (Box 16)
        - Queen's College 1981 (Box 16)
        - St. John's 1973 (Box 16)
        - St. John's 1982 (Box 16)
        - Sam Houston State 1978 (Box 16)
        - South Florida 1980 (Box 16)
        - Tennessee 1971 (Box 16)
        - Toronto 1982 (Box 16)
        - Western Michigan 1983 (Box 16)
        - Wisconsin (Milwaukee) 1972 (Box 16)
        - Wright State 1977 (Box 16)
      - Correspondence
        - Bidlack's "Personal File," 1949-1981, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Esch, Representative Marvin L. 1969-1976 (Box 16)
        - Holley, Dean Edward G. 1971-1984, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - "Peculiar letters," 1971-1978 (Box 16)
        - Pursell, Representative Carl 1978-1983 (Box 16)
        - General
          (arranged in six-month groupings beginning in 1974 and in one-year groupings before that date)
          - July 1981-June 1984, 6 folders (Box 16)
        - General January 1974-June 1981, 15 folders (Box 17)
        - General 1949-1973, 25 folders (Box 18)
      - Grant Application 1958 (Box 18)
      - Lectures, Papers, Publications, Speeches, and Testimony 1959-1984
        - Lectures
          - "Issues in Library Education from the Perspective of Accreditation," University of Oregon December 4, 1976 (Box 18)
          - "Librarians of the 1980s," September 25, 1980 for the Arizona Library Association (Box 18)
          - "Outline on Deaning," Fall 1978 for L.S.861 (Box 18)
          - "Using Public Records Advantageously," October 6, 1979 for the Ann Arbor Public Library (Box 18)
        - Papers
          - "Dewey Decimal," December 1966 at Columbia Workshop (Box 18)
          - "Fifty Years of Accreditation by the ALA," 1977 at ASIS SIG/ED Annual Meeting (Box 18)
          - "Fiscal and Economic Implications of the Two-Year Program in Library Education," March 1980 at Columbia Conference (Box 18)
          - "The Place of Specialization in the Master's Degree" (with responses from colleagues) 1979 at Allerton Conference, 2 folders (Box 18)
          - "Problems Facing Genealogists in Libraries," 1971 at Detroit (Box 18)
          - "Response to Jane Robbins Carter's Paper," 1980 at AALS Austin Conference (Box 18)
          - "Selection of a University Librarian," 1979 (Box 18)
          - "Some Economic and Demographic Realities Facing Library Education," June 1982 for Law Libraries Association (Box 18)
        - Publications
          - "Accreditation," 1975 ALA Yearbook (Box 19)
          - "Bibliographic Instruction," 1976 Journal of Academic Librarianship (Box 19)
          - "Genealogy as it Relates to Library Service," 1978 ALA Yearbook (Box 19)
          - Genealogy Paper 1983 ALA Yearbook (Box 19)
          - "Michigan Bibliography: 1963," 1963 Michigan History (Box 19)
          - "1998 Sketch," 1976 Michigan Alumnus (Box 19)
          - Typewritten Catalog Cards 1959 (Box 19)
          - "University of Michigan Library School," 1974 Encyclopedia of Library and Information Science (Box 19)
        - Speeches
          - "The Dixboro Ghost," (and others) October 1962 (Box 19)
          - "Getting Started in Library Education" 1974 for ALA Teachers Section (Box 19)
          - "Inter-relationship of Genealogy and History," undated at Saginaw, Michigan (Box 19)
          - "Library School Curricula," October 20, 1971 at Michigan State University (Box 19)
          - Miscellaneous notes (Box 19)
          - "1972 Accreditation Standards," 1972 at N.Y.L.A. Conference (Box 19)
          - "Trends and Issues in Library Education Today," December 16, 1977 at Emporia State University (Box 19)
          - Untitled 1983 at MFLA in Cincinnati (Box 19)
          - Untitled, undated, in Milan for Michigan week (Box 19)
        - Testimony
          - James O'Hara's Committee September 17, 1975 (Box 19)
          - Paul Simon's Committee September 17, 1981 (Box 19)
          - Paul Simon's Committee 1982 (Box 19)
      - Oversight Committee for the State Library 1981-1983 (Box 19)
      - Resume (Box 19)
      - Scrapbook 1947-1949 (Box 19)
      - Society of American Archivists 1973-1974 (Box 19)
      - UCLA
        - Frontiers Conference Advisory Committee 1981 (Box 19)
        - Senior Fellows Program Advisory Committee 1982 (Box 19)
    - Faculty Correspondence
      - Memos from Faculty
        - 1970/71-1983/84, 13 folders (Box 19)
      - Memos to Faculty
        - 1969/70-1977/78, 10 folders (Box 19)
        - 1978/79-1983/84, 6 folders (Box 20)
    - Statistics
      - Admissions and Enrollment
        - 1965/66-1986/87, 11 folders (Box 20)
        - New Students 1969/70-1982/83 (Box 20)
        - Summary Data 1968/69-1984/85 (Box 20)
      - Degrees Awarded (Includes student lists)
        - 1926/27-1943/44 (Box 20)
        - 1953/54-1984/85, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Doctoral Students 1950/51-1977/78, 1980/81-1981/82 (Box 20)
      - Financial Aid Distribution
        - 1975/76-1982/83 (Box 20)
        - Aid to Minority Students 1970/71-1977/78 (Box 20)
      - Faculty Grade Distributions 1970/71-1983/84 (Box 20)
      - Minority Students 1965/66-1982/83 (Box 20)
    - Topical Files
      - American Library Association, Speech on Accreditation 1980 (Box 21)
      - Annual Report of the School of Library Science 1969/70-1983/84, 3 folders (Box 21)
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC)
        - Correspondence and Reports 1973-1976 (Box 21)
        - Fellowship 1972-1973 (Box 21)
      - Council on Library Resources, Professional Education and Training for Research Librarianship 1980-1984, 3 folders (Box 21)
      - Dean's Report to Alumni Spring 1975, Summer 1977, Fall 1978 (Box 21)
      - Honorary Degrees
        - 1969-1973 (Box 21)
        - Virginia Lacy Jones
          - Correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 21)
          - Dinner 1979 (Box 21)
      - Inter-Association Library Scholarship Fund Board 1965-1973 (Box 21)
      - Michigan Department of Education State Library Services, Conferences 1970, 1977 (Box 21)
      - North Central Accreditation Self-Study 1979 (Box 21)
      - Technology Based Industry Committee 1979/80 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous Files
      - ALA Accreditation Reports 1967, 1975 (Box 36)
      - Capital Campaign 1980 (Box 36)
      - Capital Planning Correspondence 1975 (Box 36)
      - Faculty Retreat 1979 (Box 36)
      - Salary Reports 1979 (Box 36)
      - Strategic Planning 1982-1983 (Box 36)
  - Robert M. Warner 1984/85-1991/92
    The Robert M. Warner (1 linear foot) subseries is arranged into three sub-subseries reflecting the three different aspects of his deanship, Dean Elect, 1984/85; Deanship, 1985/86-1991/92; and Graduate Library Interim Directorship, 1987/88-1990/91. The Dean Elect subseries contains correspondence and other materials pertaining to Warner's appointment as dean of the school and his plans for the Library School. The Deanship subseries contains materials relating to Warner's term as dean and his active involvement in school, university and professional activities. The Deanship files, which were received in to multiple accessions, are arranged in two alphabetical files titled Subject and Topical. One of the more well documented activities is the Information Symposium that Warner coordinated in 1991. This university-wide event brought educators together to discuss the changing nature of information and its role in modern society. In addition to documenting various administrative activities, the Warner material documents newly emerging attitudes about the future of the School and of the library profession. The strategic planning material, which includes curriculum committee reports and documents, is particularly strong in this area.
    Finally, the Graduate Library Interim Directorship subseries contains correspondence and other materials relating to planning and growth for the library.
    - Dean Elect 1984/85
      - Correspondence
        - Alumni 1984/85 (Box 21)
        - General 1984/85 (Box 21)
        - Library School Budget 1984/85 (Box 21)
      - Course Proposals 1985 (Box 21)
      - Curriculum Task Force 1985 (Box 21)
      - Ideas and Plans for Library School (Box 21)
      - Kochen Information Proposal 1985 (Box 21)
      - Library School Planning 1985 (Box 21)
      - Personnel 1985 (Box 21)
      - Research Task Force 1985 (Box 21)
      - Strategic Planning Retreat 1985 (Box 21)
    - Deanship 1985/86-1991/92
      - Topical File 1985/86-1991/92
        - Affirmative Action 1987/88 (Box 21)
        - Budget, Financial Analysis 1988 (Box 21)
        - Budget Priorities Committee 1988/89-1990/91 (Box 21)
        - Campus Planning 1986, 1992 (Box 21)
        - Correspondence 1985-1992, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Grants, 3M Foundation 1986 (Box 21)
        - Information Packet from R.E. Bidlack (Box 21)
        - Information Symposium
          - Comments on Committee Reports 1991 (Box 22)
          - Committees
            - Committee Nominations 1991 (Box 22)
            - Electronic Information Resources Growth and Management Committee 1990-1991 (Box 22)
            - Funding of Information Resources Committee 1990-1991 (Box 22)
            - Planning Committee 1990-1991 (Box 22)
            - User's Changing Needs Committee 1990-1991 (Box 22)
          - Correspondence 1988-1992 (Box 22)
          - Meeting Notes and Minutes 1989-1991 (Box 22)
          - Planning 1988-1989 (Box 22)
          - Press Releases and Newspaper Articles 1990-1992 (Box 22)
          - Symposium Materials 1991 (Box 22)
        - Information Symposium II 1991-1992 (Box 22)
        - Joseph Gugliemi Visit (IBM) October 21-21, 1988 (Box 22)
        - School of Education Evaluation Committee 1986 (Box 22)
        - Syracuse University Maxwell Board Dean Search 1987 (Box 22)
      - Topical File
        - Advisory Committee 1985-1991, 7 folders (Box 36)
        - Alumni Association 1984 (Box 36)
        - Annual Giving Fund 1981-1987 (Box 36)
        - Budget Materials 1985-1988 (Box 36)
        - Committee on Institutional Cooperation 1990-1991 (Box 36)
        - Computer Lab 1989 (Box 36)
        - Correspondence
          - Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1985-1992 (Box 36)
          - School of Education 1986 (Box 36)
          - Faculty 1985-1986 (Box 36)
        - Development 1985-1988 (Box 36)
        - Dougherty letter of quality of SILS students 1987 (Box 36)
        - Engineering/Joint Ph.D. program (Box 36)
        - Enrollment Planning 1990-1992 (Box 36)
        - Executive Committee 1992 (Box 36)
        - Faculty Promotion and Tenure requirements, (undated) (Box 36)
        - Faculty Research Interests 1986 (Box 36)
        - Faculty and Staff Median Salaries 1987 (Box 36)
        - Fundraising Telethon 1986 (Box 36)
        - Lab Fees Discussion 1991 (Box 36)
        - Research Profile 1988 (Box 36)
        - Strategic Planning
          - Strategic Planning Committee 1985-1988, 2 folders (Box 36)
          - Strategic Plans 1983, 1985, 1989 (Box 36)
          - Strategic Planning Retreats 1986-1988, 4 folders (Box 36)
    - Graduate Library Interim Directorship 1987/88-1990/91
      - Correspondence 1988-1991 (Box 22)
      - Library Planning 1989, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Management Review 1989 (Box 22)
      - Speeches 1990 (Box 22)
  - Richard M. Dougherty (acting Dean)
    The Richard M. Dougherty subseries documents the activities and administration of the school during his short tenure as Interim Dean.
    - Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 36)
    - Development Fund 1985 (Box 36)
    - Fundraising 1984 (Box 36)
    - Library Research Institute 1984 (Box 36)
    - Research Committee 1985 (Box 36)
    - Retreat 1984 (Box 36)
    - Strategic Planning Committee 1984-1985 (Box 36)
  - Martha Pollock
    The Martha Pollack dean's files (2007/2008-2009/2010) subseries includes electronic records related to academic programs, admissions, enrollment, faculty searches and reviews, budgets and development, and meetings of various bodies in the school and at the university. The subseries also documents the School of Information's administrative separation from the Rackham School of Graduate Studies, the development of a graduate program in health informatics and undergraduate program in informatics, and the transfer of the school's offices to North Quad in 2010. The records were received in a 20011 accession.
    - Administrative records
      - Associate Dean of Academic Affairs (ADAA) 2009
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2032 ]
      - Associate Dean for Research (ADR) 2009
      - American Library Association (ALA) Re-accreditation
        - Correspondence, reports, documentation, and notice of continued accreditation 2009-2010
        - Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET) example material 2005-2006
      - Association for Library and Information Science Education (ALISE) 2007-2009
      - Alumni Board (meeting materials, rosters, board biographies)
      - Academic Program Group (APG)
        - Budget Subcommittee 2009-2010
        - Development Subcommittee 2008
        - Subcommittees (general) 2009-2010
        - Information and policy 2007-2010
        - Meeting summaries, agendas, and notes 2007-2010
        - Quality reports to provost (by Schools and Colleges) circa 2008
        - Reaccreditation (for U-M via the Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools) 2007-2009
        - School for Deans 2008
      - Arts on Earth 2008-2010
      - Alternative Spring Break (ASB) 2010
      - Budget 2005-2011
      - Centers (U-M) circa 2008
      - Communications
        - Communications before Fall 2009, 2007-2009
        - Communications Survey 2008
        - Website (guidelines and proposal for creating online content) 2009-2011
      - Community Informatics circa 2009
      - Computing (storage costs, cloud computing, IT rationalization, etc.) 2009-2010
      - Corporate and foundation relations 2008-2010
      - Dean's Advisory Committee (DAC) 2008-2009
      - Dean's Groups (includes iDeans and IT Deans groups) 2008-2010
      - Dean Transition Information 2010
      - Development 2007-2009
      - Digital Studies (reports) 2009